<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="administration">
	<title>RCE Administration</title>
	<sect1>
		<title>SSH Uplink Networks</title>
		<para>
			To exchange tool computation services between organizations,
			some sort
			of network connection must
			be established. As many
			organizations are (understandably) reluctant to
			open ports into their
			networks,
			the Uplink approach is based on connecting to a shared
			coordination/forwarding server called a "relay".
		</para>
		<para>
			This relay server is typically placed outside of any
			organization's
			protected network, e.g. on a rented
			server or in the DMZ
			of one of the involved organizations.
		</para>
		<para>
			Due to the exposed nature of this relay server, it is designed
			to be
			secure by default. There is only
			one way of connecting to it,
			which is the encrypted and authenticated
			SSH protocol. The protocol
			transmitted over SSH is designed to be concise and easily audited.
		</para>
		<para> Development is focused on placing as little trust as possible into the relay server.
			Technical steps are being taken to limit what data can be monitored at the relay server.
			Some of these features, however, are <emphasis>not</emphasis> implemented in the
			experimental Uplink feature in RCE 10 yet. In all RCE 10.x versions, data transmitted to
			and from tools is safely encrypted against unauthorized access from
				<emphasis>outside</emphasis> users, through the standard security features provided
			by the SSH protocol. However, all data could theoretically still be observed by
			administrators of the relay server. <emphasis>If this is unacceptable in your setup,
				please wait for the RCE 11 release, in which the Uplink feature is scheduled for
				non-experimental release.</emphasis></para>
		<para>
			A typical Uplink setup between two or more organizations
			involves:
		</para>
		<para>
			The Uplink relay server (a specially configured RCE instance) in
			a
			location that is accessible from all
			organization's networks.
		</para>
		<para>
			This relay server opens a SSH port, with one or more sets of
			credentials
			for each organization.
			Typically, only a single login is
			needed for each project group within an
			organization; see
			below.
		</para>
		<para>
			An Uplink SSH gateway node (again, a specially configured RCE
			instance)
			in each organization's
			network.
		</para>
		<para>
			This node is the only one that actually establishes an SSH
			connection to
			the relay.
		</para>
		<para>
			It is typically centrally administered, and not used for any
			other
			end-user work.
		</para>
		<para>
			A benefit of this setup is that the SSH login credentials are
			only
			required to be present on that
			machine. Additionally, this reduces
			the number of SSH logins that must be
			configured on the
			server side, as
			it is effectively shared by all users with access to this
			(internal)
			SSH gateway.
		</para>
		<para>
			This node opens one or more default RCE network connection ports
			towards
			the internal
			network. Access to this can be restricted using
			standard internal network
			policies as needed.
		</para>
		<para>
			End users can then use their individual RCE instances to connect
			to the
			SSH gateway node (using
			RCE's default network features).
		</para>
		<para>
			Once this setup is complete, users can access tool compute
			services
			published by their or one of the
			other organizations in the
			form of virtual tools within their RCE
			networks.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Example of a Cross-Organization Network</title>
		<para>The following figure gives an example of how such a
			cross-organization network could be structured:
		</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Example RCE network</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/RCE-uplink-network.png"
						contentwidth="400" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The four project partners in the example all have an internal
			network of RCE instances which are connected by standard RCE
			connections. Uplink connections to a relay server are used to connect
			between the different partners. The relay server is located outside
			of the organizations networks, and only the relay server has to be
			reachable via SSH over the internet. Typically, for each organization
			one RCE instance (called SSH gateway) established an SSH connections
			to this relay server. All other instances in the institution’s
			internal network can be connected to it by standard RCE connections
			and still publish tools to the other partners/ access tools published
			by other partners.
		</para>
		<para>
			Each institution in the example has a different internal setup, all
			of which are possible:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para> Partner A has a dedicated RCE server where the published tools are
						located, which is connected to the SSH gateway by an RCE connection. All
						other RCE users in the internal network are connected to this server </para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para> Partner B has put all the tools directly on the SSH gateway instance.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para> In Partner C's network, some tools are located on the SSH gateway, but
						some tools are also published by users directly on their own machines. As
						long as they are connected to the SSH gateway also those tools can be
						published to the other partners. </para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para> Partner D has no tool server, instead the users’ computers connect
						directly to the relay server. </para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Notes and Recommendations: RCE's Default Network Connections
		</title>
		<para>For default connections, an arbitrary number of incoming network
			ports can be configured.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Notes and Recommendations: RCE's SSH Port</title>
	<para> When creating SSH accounts using the built-in administration
		text mode UI, there is an issue when entering passwords including the
		"@" character. This does not weaken security in any way, but can be
		confusing for end users when their correctly entered password does not
		work. It may be advisable to inform users about this. </para>
	<para>Hashing SSH passwords with external BCrypt tools and entering them into the JSON file
			containing SSH accounts (either manually or via scripts) should theoretically work, but
			is neither tested nor supported at this point. Please contact us at
				<email>rce@dlr.de</email> if this is relevant for you.</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
