<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>VAMPzero Initializer Component Usage</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>The VAMPzero initializer provides a tool to create an input data set for the conceptual
            aircraft design tool VAMPzero via a user-friendly graphical interface. The output
            consists of a CPACS file that can be forwarded to a copy of VAMPzero.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Rationale</title>
        <para>The basic idea is that RCE in combination with the Common Parametric Aircraft
            Configuration Schema (CPACS) and the conceptual aircraft design code VAMPzero enable new
            users to easily start their aircraft design. Hence, it is important to provide means to
            easily manipulate the input settings of VAMPzero without being forced to interact with
            the CPACS file directly. In consequence, the VAMPzero Initializer fulfils this task, as
            it can create new or manipulate existing input data sets for VAMPzero. The output of
            the VAMPzero Initializer is a CPACS file that contains the &lt;toolspecific> input for
            VAMPzero. Hence, an identical file can be created manually. In a subsequent step the
            file needs to be forwarded to an instance of VAMPzero to perform the conceptual aircraft
            design.</para>
        <para>All input values of VAMPzero are available. Nevertheless, there is no check whether
            the input setting is actually reasonable or not. For further information on VAMPzero and
            its parameters please visit: <ulink url="https://software.dlr.de/p/vampzero/home/"
                >https://software.dlr.de/p/vampzero/home/</ulink></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>On the "Initialization" tab in the properties view you may edit or define new
            parameters to the aircraft. Each parameter, e.g., reference Area, is adjacent to a
            component, e.g., wing, and a discipline, e.g., geometry. Hence, first the component and
            the discipline must be selected to obtain a list of possible inputs. If you want to
            remove a parameter from an input set you may use the revert button.</para>
        <para>You may either enter a value or a factor. A value overwrites VAMPzero's initial value.
            A factor is simply multiplicated to the VAMPzero calculation method, much like a normal
            technology factor.</para>
        <para>Via the load configuration button it is possible to load a pre-defined set of input
            values.</para>
        <para>To finalize the input data set you must press the "Create CPACS" button. The output of
            the VAMPzero Initializer component may then be connected via the draw connection tool to
            another instance of VAMPzero.</para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
