<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>CPACS Writer Component Usage</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para>The CPACS Writer component saves incoming CPACS content as an xml file on the local file
            system. It has a runtime GUI to show the CPACS file in TiGL Viewer.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>On the “Target” tab you can select the target folder where the file will be stored. If
            you select the option “Overwrite CPACS file each run” the filename will be “cpacs.xml”
            and the file will be overwritten each time the component runs. If you do not select this
            option a new file will be written on each run with a filename following the scheme
            “cpacs_[iteration count]_[timestamp].xml”.</para>
        <para>You can define the scheduling of the static input channels on the tab
            “Inputs/Outputs”. You are also able to add dynamic input or output channels here. Thus
            it is possible to map single values into the XML dataset via XPATH declaration.
            Moreover, you can select single values in order to write them in an output
            channel.
            <note>Search for the XPathChooser help in the User Guide (3. Usage -> 2. Workflows -> 2.3 Workflow components) 
            to garner further information about the usage of XPaths.</note>
        </para>
        <para>On the “Workflow Data” tab you can select whether to store history data for each
            component run or not.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Runtime GUI</title>
        <para>Double clicking on the CPACS Writer component during or after workflow execution opens
            the “CPACS Geometry” view where the current CPACS content is shown. <phrase os="windows"
                >By clicking the button “Show CPACS dataset in TIGL Viewer” the corresponding view
                “TIGL Viewer” will show the CPACS geometry in the TiGL Viewer, if that viewer is
                configured. See the help entry for the TiGL Viewer component and the configuration
                reference for more information on how to configure the TiGL viewer.</phrase></para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
