<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>Design of Experiments Component Usage</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>The Design of Experiment component sends values (floating-point numbers) to other components. The values
            are either generated on the base of a design method or are provided by a custom design
            table. The values can be used to sample a solution within a bounded space. They are
            independent to each other.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>First, outputs must be defined. Each output is of type float and has a lower and an
            upper bound. The definition of inputs is optional. If inputs are defined, the DOE
            component maps one set of output values to one set of input values. I.e., output values
            are sent as soon as input values (corresponding to previously sent output values) are
            received. Queuing of input values as not allowed. If no inputs are defined, the output
            values are sent all at once at workflow start.</para>
        <para>Second, the design method must be selected. You can choose between four
            methods:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Factorial_experiment">Full
                factorial design</ulink></para> </listitem>
            <listitem> <para><ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin_hypercube_sampling">Latin
                hypercube design</ulink></para> </listitem>
            <listitem><para><ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monte_Carlo_method">Monte Carlo
                design</ulink></para> </listitem>
            <listitem><para>Custom design</para> </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The first three methods generate the output values on the base of established design
            methods (see links above). For two of them, the values are random. You can choose a seed
            in order to reuse the same values later. The number of samples can be defined with the
            option "Number of levels"/"Desired runs" and can be communicated to other components
            using the "Number of samples" output, which is sent out on the first iteration of the
            DOE component.</para>
        <para>The last method allows to define a custom design table. The table at the bottom is
            editable and values can be entered. The table can be saved as a csv file and can be
            re-loaded later on. It is also possible to define a custom sample range by modifying the
            "Start at sample #" and "End at sample #" option.</para>
        <para>For help concerning nested and fault-tolerant loop settings, see the general section "Workflows" in the user guide.</para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
