<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>Output Writer Component Usage</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>The Output Writer stores outputs from other components on the local file system. </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Rationale</title>
        <para> The Output Writer receives inputs from other workflow components and saves them in a
            pre-configured folder. The inputs can either be files or directories, which are written
            directly to the local file system, or inputs of simple data types (Boolean, Float,
            Integer, Short Text), which are written into text files of a user-defined format. </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>Output to save must be send to the Output Writer via inputs. If you add a new input of
            type file or directory, you must define the desired target name and path (of the file or
            directory). Both of them can be created using placeholders:</para>
        <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image001.png"/></para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Target file/directory:</emphasis> The name the file will be
            given on the local file system. You can insert different placeholders by clicking the
            “Insert” button. The provided placeholders are:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Component name]: Name of the Output Writer component in the
                        workflow.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Input name]: Name of the input you define at the top of this
                        dialog.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Timestamp]: Date and time at file creation.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Timestamp at workflow start]: Date and time at workflow start.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Workflow name]: Name of the workflow.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Execution count]: Execution count of the Output Writer.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Original filename]: The name the file/directory had before it was sent to
                        the Output Writer.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>It is possible to combine placeholders within a single name.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Target folder:</emphasis> The folder, where the file or
            directory should be stored. It is relative to the [root] folder (see below). Currently,
            only one sub folder below the [root] folder is supported. You can either select a
            folder, which was already used for other inputs or you can “create” a new one just by
            defining a new folder name within in the text box. Again, the folder name can contain
            placeholders.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Root folder:</emphasis> The files and directories received via
            the inputs will be saved to the [root] folder. You can either select the [root] folder
            at workflow start or you can define a “static” one within the component’s configuration
            tab below the inputs table. This folder is used on every workflow execution. Note:
            Defining a static folder might cause problems, if you execute the workflow on another
            RCE node (e.g. the defined hard drive doesn’t exist on the other machine).</para>
        <para> For inputs of simple data types, you only have to specify the type of the input in
            the “add input” dialog. If you are using such inputs, you also have to specify targets
            in the table below the “Inputs” table. A target receives the values of one or more
            simple data inputs and writes them into a text file of user-specified format. Several
            targets can be specified in one Output Writer. However, each input can only be written
            into one target.<note>
                <para>The Output Writer only writes output into a target file when values for ALL of
                    the selected inputs have arrived. I.e. it is expected that for each iteration
                    exactly one value for each of the inputs arrives. </para>
            </note></para>
        <para> In the “Add target” dialog you have to specify the following:</para>
        <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image002.png"/></para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Target file:</emphasis> The name the file will be given on the
            local file system. You can insert different placeholders by clicking the “Insert”
            button. The provided placeholders are:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Component name]: Name of the Output Writer component in the
                        workflow.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Timestamp at workflow start]: Date and time at workflow start.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Workflow name]: Name of the workflow.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Target folder:</emphasis> The folder where the file should be
            stored. It is relative to the [root] folder (see below). Currently, only one sub folder
            below the [root] folder is supported. You can either select a folder, which was already
            used for other inputs or you can “create” a new one just by defining a new folder name
            within in the text box. Again, the folder name can contain placeholders.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Inputs involved:</emphasis> Here you can select which inputs
            should be written into the target file. Only inputs of simple data types are shown here.
            Inputs that are already selected for another target are not selectable.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">File header:</emphasis> Here you can define the header of the
            output file, which will be written once at the beginning of the target file (only if
            “Append” is selected in the “file handling” dropdown). You can insert different
            placeholders by clicking the “Insert” button. The provided placeholders are:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Linebreak]: A linebreak.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Timestamp]: Date and time at file creation.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Execution count]: Execution count of the Output Writer.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Value(s) format:</emphasis> Here you can define the format of
            the input values for one iteration. You can insert different placeholders by clicking
            the “Insert” button. The provided placeholders are:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[xy]: The received value for a selected input xy.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Linebreak]: A linebreak. (Linebreaks will not be inserted automatically
                        between iterations).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Timestamp]: Date and time when the inputs were received .</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>[Execution count]: Execution count of the Output Writer.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">File handling:</emphasis> Here you can select one of the
            following options:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Append: The standard option where the inputs of all iterations are written
                        to the same file. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Auto-Rename: For each iteration, a new file will be created for each
                        iteration.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Override: Like Auto-Rename, but the file from the previous iteration will
                        be overwritten, so you have one file that only contains the inputs from the
                        last iteration. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
