<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="network">
	<title>Connecting RCE instances via the RCE network or via SSH connections</title>
	<para>RCE provides two possibilities to connect your RCE instance to other RCE instances and to use
		the user-integrated tools and components published on those instances: The RCE network
		connections and SSH connections. RCE connections are meant to be used only in a trusted
		network (e.g. your institution's internal network). The RCE network traffic is currently
			<emphasis>not encrypted</emphasis>. This means that it is <emphasis>not
			secure</emphasis> to expose RCE server ports to untrusted networks like the internet. In
		the case that it is not possible or not secure to use RCE connections, SSH connections
		provide a more secure alternative. The following table compares the two connection
			types:<table frame="all">
			<title>Connection types</title>
			<tgroup cols="6">
				<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.06*"/>
				<colspec colname="newCol4" colnum="2" colwidth="1.7*"/>
				<colspec colname="newCol9" colnum="3" colwidth="2.55*"/>
				<colspec colname="newCol6" colnum="4" colwidth="1.67*"/>
				<colspec colname="newCol7" colnum="5" colwidth="1.98*"/>
				<colspec colname="c2" colnum="6" colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Connection type</entry>
						<entry>Access to all published tools</entry>
						<entry>Supporting all RCE network functions (e.g. remote monitoring)</entry>
						<entry>Encrypted traffic</entry>
						<entry>Using login name and password or RSA key</entry>
						<entry>Symmetrical</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>RCE connections</entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">yes</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">yes</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">no</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">no</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">yes</emphasis></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>SSH connections</entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">yes</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">no</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">yes</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">yes</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">no</emphasis></entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table></para>
	<sect2>
		<title>RCE Network Connections</title>
		<para>RCE connections are meant to be used only in a trusted network (e.g. your
			institution's internal network). To build up a network of RCE instances, at least one of
			the instances has to be configured as a server (see the "Configuration" section or the
			sample configuration file "Relay server" for details).</para>
		<para>On the client side, RCE network connections can be added in the "network" view by clicking
			"Add network connection" and entering the hostname and port of an RCE server instance.
			The connections are shown in the "RCE Network"->"Connections" subtree. They can also be
			edited, connected and disconnected in the network view. However, the changes made here
			are not saved in the configuration yet, i.e. they will be lost when RCE is closed or
			restarted. To permanently add connections, you can edit the configuration file (see the
			"Configuration" section for details). </para>
		<para>In the "RCE Network" -> "Instances" subtree all RCE instances in the network are
			listed. When expanding the entry for an instance, you can see monitoring data like CPU
			or RAM usage for this instance, and the published components and tools of this instance
			(if it has any).</para>
		<para>The published components and tools of the other instances in your network are also shown in
			the palette of the Workflow Editor. From there, you can use them in your workflows just
			like your local components and tools. When you start a workflow, in the "Execute
			Workflow" wizard there is an overview which component will be run on which RCE instance.
			If a component is available on several instances, you can choose here on which instance
			it should be run. In the same wizard, you can also choose another instance as the
			"Controller Target Instance", which means that the workflow execution will be controlled
			by this instance (see the section "Configuration Parameters" for more information). This
			can be useful when you start a long-running workflow where all components are run on
			remote instances and you do not want to keep your local computer connected all the
			time.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>SSH Remote Access Connections</title>
		<para>SSH connections provide a more secure alternative to the standard RCE connections and can be
			used to access tools remotely. The published tools are shown in the palette of the
			client's Workflow Editor (this may take a few seconds after connecting, as the tool list
			is fetched from the remote hosts every few seconds). From there, you can use them in
			your workflows just like your local components and tools. Differently from tools
			accessed by RCE network connections, in this case the component is shown to be executed
			on your local instance in the Workflow Execution wizard.</para>
		<para>Also workflows that were published on the remote instance (for information about the
			publishing see section "Remote Tool and Workflow Access") are shown as components in the
			palette of the client's Workflow Editor in the group "SSH Remote Access Workflows" (if
			the client runs RCE 7.1 or newer). These remote workflows can be added to workflows and
			executed like local components/tools.</para>
		<sect3>
			<title>Configuring an RCE instance as an SSH server</title>
			<para>The RCE instance that publishes the tool, or another instance connected to it by
				RCE network connections, has to be configured as an RCE remote access server (see
				the "Configuration" section or the sample configuration file "Remote access server"
				for details). </para>
			<note>
				<para>When configuring an SSH account using a key file, note that for using key files, both
					server and client have to run RCE 7.1 or newer and that only RSA-Keys in the
					OpenSSH format are supported by RCE. You can generate such keys on Linux e.g.
					using the "ssh-keygen" tool (which creates the correct format by default). On
					Windows, you can use the software "puttygen" to generate a key (choose the type
					"SSH-2 RSA") and convert it to the OpenSSH format ("Conversions"->"Export
					OpenSSH key" in puttygen). </para>
			</note>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Configuring an RCE instance as an SSH client</title>
			<para>On the client side, SSH connections can be added in the "network" view by clicking
				"Add SSH Remote Access Connection". In the following dialog, enter the hostname and
				port of an RCE instance that provides an SSH server as well as the user name and the
				authentication data of an SSH account configured on this instance. Depending on the
				SSH account, you have to authenticate using a passphrase or by an RSA private key
				file. If your private key is protected by a passphrase, select the authentication
				type "Keyfile with passphrase protection", else select "Keyfile without passphrase
				protection".</para>
			<para>The connections are shown in the "SSH Remote Access"->"SSH Remote Access Connections"
				subtree. They can also be edited, connected and disconnected in the "network" view.
				It is possible to store passphrases using the Eclipse Secure Storage Mechanism (this
				is only available on Windows). However, the changes made here are not saved in the
				configuration yet, i.e. they will be lost when RCE is closed or restarted. To
				permanently add SSH connections, you can edit the configuration file (see the
				"Configuration" section for details). However, it is not possible yet to store the
				passphrases for such connections permanently.</para>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>Example Structure of an RCE network with several project partners</title>
		<para>This section describes how an RCE network with several project partners could be
			structured. RCE provides two different types of connections between RCE instances which
			can both be used to access published tools:</para>
		<para>Standard RCE connections are meant to be used in a trusted (internal) network, as the
			data exchanged via those connections is not encrypted. These connections are
			bidirectional and allow to share more data than just the information about published
			tools (e.g. they can be used to access data about executed workflows on another
			instance).</para>
		<para>RCE SSH connections use the SSH protocol to provide an encrypted connection. They are
			meant to securely connect RCE instances from different institutions over the internet.
			These connections are one-directional and allow the client to run published tools and
			workflows on the server (of course, both instances can be configured as client AND
			server at the same time if necessary so they can use each other’s tools).</para>
		<para>In practice, most partners will probably use both types of connections: RCE
			connections to connect different RCE instances within their institution and SSH
			connections to connect to the other partners. The following figure gives an example of
			how such a project network could be structured:</para>
		<figure>
				<title>Example RCE network</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/RCE-SSH-network.png" contentwidth="400"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The four project partners in the example all have an internal network of RCE instances which
			are connected by standard RCE connections. SSH connections are used to connect between
			the different partners. Therefore, each partner who wants to publish tools to other
			partners has one RCE instance which is configured as an SSH server. Only this one
			instance per institution has to be reachable via SSH over the internet, all other
			instances in the institution’s internal network can be connected to it by standard RCE
			connections and still publish tools to the other partners/access tools published by
			other partners.</para>
		<para>In the example, the RCE instances in Partner A’s network can access the tools
			published in Partner C’s network and vice versa. One of the instances from Partner D can
			access Partner C’s tools; and all the partners can access the tools in Partner B’s
			network.</para>
		<para>Each institution in the example has a different internal setup, all of which are
			possible:</para>
		<para>Partner A has a dedicated RCE server where the published tools are located, which is
			connected to the SSH server by an RCE connection. All other RCE users in the internal
			network are connected to this server.</para>
		<para>Partner B has put all the tools directly on the SSH server.</para>
		<para>In Partner C’s network, some tools are located on the SSH server, but some tools are
			also published by users directly on their own machines. As long as they are connected to
			the SSH server, also those tools can be used by the other partners. </para>
		<para>Partner D has not published any tools and has no SSH server, instead the users’
			computers connect directly to the other partner’s SSH servers. </para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
