<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>CPACS Tool Properties</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>Configure the CPACS tool specific values.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>Fill in the following values to make your tool using the CPACS specific features, e.g.
            input and output mapping.<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Incoming CPACS endpoint name:</emphasis> Select the
                        input that represents the incoming CPACS file. This input must be configured
                        on the “Inputs and Outputs” page.<note>
                            <para>The data type of this input must be “File”. Usage must be
                                “required”.</para>
                        </note></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Input mapping file:</emphasis> Select or enter the
                        mapping file for input mapping. Supported file extensions are “.xml” for
                        classic mapping and“.xsl” for advanced XSLT-mapping.<note>
                            <para>The path must be relative to the tool directory configured on the
                                “Launch Settings” page. The file chooser dialog regards that
                                fact.</para>
                        </note></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Tool input filename:</emphasis> Enter the filename
                        of the input file the integrated tool will access. This file will be
                        generated as a result of the incoming CPACS file mapped with the incoming
                        XPath variables, the input mapping and, if selected, the tool specific input.<note>
                            <para>The path must be relative to the tool directory configured on the
                                “Launch Settings” page.</para>
                        </note></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Tool output filename:</emphasis> Enter the filename
                        of the output file of your tool. This file will be accessed during the
                        output mapping execution.<note>
                            <para>The path must be relative to the tool directory configured on the
                                “Launch Settings” page.</para>
                        </note></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Output mapping file:</emphasis> Select or enter the
                        mapping file for output mapping. Supported file extensions are “.xml” for
                        classic mapping and “.xsl” for advanced XSLT-mapping.Note: The path must be
                        relative to the tool directory configured on the “Launch Settings” page. The
                        file chooser dialog regards that fact.<note>
                            <para>The path must be relative to the tool directory configured on the
                                “Launch Settings” page. The file chooser dialog regards that
                                fact.</para>
                        </note></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">CPACS result filename:</emphasis> Enter the filename
                        for the resulting CPACS-file. This file will be the mapped tool output file
                        and represents the outgoing CPACS file. It is the also the basis for dynamic
                        output values in the later workflow configuration accessed via XPath.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Outgoing CPACS endpoint name:</emphasis> Select the
                        output the CPACS result file will be sent to. This output must be configured
                        on the “Inputs and Outputs”page.Note: The data type of this input must be “File”.<note>
                            <para>The data type of this input must be “File”.</para>
                        </note></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Merge static tool specific input:</emphasis> If selected the
                        integrated tool will work with tool specific input and the following values
                        need to be configured.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Tool specific input file:</emphasis> Select or enter
                        the XML file with the tool specific input.<note>
                            <para>The path must be relative to the tool directory configured on the
                                “Launch Settings” page. The file chooser dialog regards that
                                fact.</para>
                        </note></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Tool specific input mapping file:</emphasis> Select
                        or enter the mapping file for tool specific mapping. Supported file
                        extensions are “.xml” for classic mapping and “.xsl” for advanced XSLT-mapping.<note>
                            <para>The path must be relative to the tool directory configured on the
                                “Launch Settings” page. The file chooser dialog regards that
                                fact.</para>
                        </note></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Only run on changed inputs:</emphasis> If selected
                        the tool will only run on changed inputs. Therefore the tool input file and
                        incoming directories are verified. If there are no changes detected the
                        incoming CPACS file will be mapped with the result of the previous
                        run.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
