<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>Input Provider Component Usage</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para>The Input Provider component sends values to inputs of other components.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Rationale</title>
        <para>The Input Provider sends values to other components, e.g. as starting values.
            Therefore, the Input Provider writes specified values to its outputs. The outputs must
            be connected to the inputs of the other components. The values are sent once and
            immediately after the workflow has been started. </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>For each value to send you need to create an output for the Input Provider component
            by clicking the "Add..." button next to the outputs table. For each output you can
            decide whether to define the value directly or to define it at workflow start by
            (un-)checking the check box "Define at workflow start".</para>
        <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image001.png"/></para>
        <para>If it is defined directly it is stored in the workflow file. If you share the
            workflow with others the defined values will be shared as well.</para>
        <para>If it is defined at workflow start only a placeholder is stored in the workflow file.
            It will be replaced with the actual value defined at workflow start. If you share the
            workflow with others only the placeholder will be shared and the other person needs to
            define the value at workflow start by herself.</para>
        <para>If you like to send files or directories to other components you have three options. You can choose the option that suits you best. In terms of workflow sharing, consider the following:<orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the file/directory to send at workflow start (you will be asked for
                        selection in the workflow execution wizard). Choose this option if you like
                        to share the workflow (.wf file) with others and don't want to share the
                        file/directory (e.g. because it contains sensitive data).</para>
                    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image004.png"/></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the file/directory from the project in the workspace where the
                        workflow file is stored. Choose that option if you like to share the
                        workflow (.wf file) as well as the file/directory with others. In that case,
                        you need to share the whole project (e.g. as an archive file - right-click
                        on the project and export it as an archive file). The other person needs to
                        import that project into the RCE workspace. The workflow will run out-of-box
                        using the file/directory of the shared project.</para>
                    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image002.png"/></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the file/directory from file system. Choose that options if you
                        don't like to share the workflow with others at all and if the
                        file/directory needs to remain at a specified place in the local file
                        system.</para>
                    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image005.png"/></para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist></para>
        <para>You will see your outputs in the table similar like this:</para>
        <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image006.png"/></para>
        <para>After that, you can connect the outputs from the Input Provider to any other
            compatible input from other components. The values (either defined directly or defined
            at workflow start) will be sent to the connected inputs of the other components
            immediately after the workflow has been started.</para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
