<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="operating_systems">
    <title>Compatible Operating Systems</title>
    <para>RCE releases are provided for Windows and Linux. It is regularly tested on<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>CentOS 7</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Debian 8</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop ("SLED") 12 SP2</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Windows 7</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Windows 10</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Windows Server 2012 R2</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>It is also confirmed to run (but not as thoroughly tested) on<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Mint 18</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop ("SLED") 11 SP2</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ubuntu 16.04 LTS</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>openSUSE Leap 42.1</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Windows 8.1</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    <sect2>
        <title>Support of 32 Bit Operating Systems</title>
        <para>Starting with release 8.0.0, RCE is only shipped for 64 bit systems. If you still
            require 32 bit packages, you can continue to use previous RCE releases, but there will
            be no standard feature or bugfix updates for them.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
        <title>Known Issues</title>
        <sect3>
            <title>KDE on Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7</title>
        <para>On Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7 with KDE 4, RCE (like any other Eclipse-based
            application) can cause a segmentation fault at startup. If you encounter such an issue,
            you can try choosing a different GTK2 theme:</para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Open the <emphasis role="bold">System Settings </emphasis>application
                        (systemsettings).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Go to <emphasis role="bold">Application Appearence</emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Open <emphasis role="bold">GTK</emphasis> page</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Switch the GTK2 theme to "Raleigh" or "Adwaita" and click on <emphasis
                            role="bold">Apply</emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
         <title>KDE with Oxygen</title>
        <para>On Unix Systems using KDE as desktop environment and Oxygen as theme it can happen that RCE crashes when certain GUI elements are shown.
            It is a known issue in the theme Oxygen and happens on other Eclipse-based applications as well. If you encounter such an issue, 
            please choose a different theme like "Raleigh" or "Adwaita".</para>
            
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
        <title>Jython scripts are executed sequentially</title>
        <para>The Script component can use Jython for the evaluation of scripts and the pre- and
                postprocessing of integrated tools always uses Jython. Due to a known bug in the
                Jython implementation it is not possible to execute several Jython instances in
                parallel. Therefore, the execution will be done sequentially. If several Script
                components should be executed in parallel, Python should be used  instead. </para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
        <title>32-bit Java is not supported</title>
        <para>Running RCE with a 32-bit Java Runtime Environment doesn't work. On some operating
                systems an error dialog will be displayed in this case, on some other systems
                nothing will happen at all. Therefore, always make sure a 64-bit Java Runtime
                Environment is used to run RCE.</para>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
