<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>Inputs and Outputs</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>Define the inputs and outputs the component for the tool should have in an RCE
            workflow.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>On this page, the inputs and outputs for the component are defined. Their behavior is
            the same as other inputs or outputs of other components, but they will always be static.
            That means no user can add or remove inputs or outputs that were defined here. However
            the handling and the constraint options can be customized when the workflow is being
            created. In the wizard you can define which options can be chosen and which one is
            default. It is not mandatory to define inputs and outputs. If there are no inputs, the
            component will run once at workflow start and will be finished then.</para>
        <para>As for the inputs, you can choose the data types File and Directory. If you do so, it
            is possible to define a file or directory name (File/Dir). Thereby the incoming
            file/directory will always be renamed to it.</para>
        <para>If no value is entered, the file/directory will have its original name.</para>
        <para>Verification allows you to manually review tool results and verify them. Before these
            results are processed by a running workflow and used by other components, you have to
            approve them manually. For approving or rejecting an output, you insert a generated
            verification key into the dialog under 'Run' -> 'Verify tool results'. By default this
            verification key is stored in tool working directory. But you can also store it at a
            custom location on the tool's machine. Additionally you can get the verification key via
            email.</para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
