<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>Tool Description</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>Define some characteristics of the tool such as name or icon and give some information
            about yourself.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>On this page, some characteristics of the tool for the integrated component are
            defined. Information for the tool user or graphical elements is optional.</para>
        <para>Required fields:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>                                
                                <para><emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> This field defines the
                                    name of the component. The name is very important, because the
                                    tool will be displayed in the workflow editor palette with this
                                    name. Note that the name must not contain special characters.
                                    The name will not be accepted if there is another locally
                                    created tool with the same name. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>Optional fields:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Icon Path:</emphasis> An icon for the tool can be
                        selected here. At best, it is larger than 32x32 pixels and has the same
                        width and height. You can select to copy it into the configuration folder,
                        so there is no absolute path link for it any more.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Group Name:</emphasis> This defines the group in the
                        workflow editor palette in which the component will be shown.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Documentation:</emphasis> Here you can choose to add
                        a documentation file for your tool. Note that the file must be a PDF or a TXT
                        document and it must not be greater than 50 MB.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Description:</emphasis> You can provide a
                        description of your tool here, which can be seen by other users when
                        configuring a workflow.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Name/E-Mail:</emphasis> You can provide some contact
                        information about yourself in this field, for example if someone has
                        questions or wants to provide suggestions.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para> 
    </sect1>
</chapter>
