<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>Tool Properties</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>Define properties for the tool, which can be used as parameters later in all scripts
            and can be configured when a workflow is set up.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>Properties are a means to let the user of the integrated tool configure some
            attributes when creating a workflow. For example, if your tool is able to run with
            multiple cores, you can define a key “numCores” and later add it as placeholder in your
            command execution script or pre/post execution script (e.g. “tool.exe
            ${prop:numCores}”). This key will then be shown in the properties tab in the workflow
            editor and the value for it can be defined there.</para>
        <para>Properties have a display name that makes them more readable for others. Also, a
            default value can be defined, to provide some useful presettings.</para>
        <para>It is not mandatory to define properties.</para>
        <para>Since RCE 8.0 it is possible to define properties as placeholders. With this option,
            which is activated in the properties view of the tool component, the user can define
            that the value for the selected property is not defined while editing the workflow, but
            at workflow start. </para>
        <para>While the use of properties allows a great amount of flexibility, they also easily
            lead to inadvertent security issues. Consider, e.g., a tool that copies some data to a
            configurable directory and removes that directory after its computation as part of
            cleanup. Malicious users may set the configuration directory to some vital system
            directory and cause the tool to remove that directory on termination. To prevent users
            from creating such security issues by accident, RCE does not allow the use of property
            values containing <code>\"</code>, ASCII-characters in the range
                <code>0x00</code>-<code>0x1f</code>, <code>\\</code>, <code>/</code>,
                <code>\*</code>, <code>\?</code>. Moreover, RCE prevents the use of <code>%</code>
            on Windows systems, and of <code>`</code> and <code>\$</code> on Linux systems.</para>
        <para>If you would like to allow your users to supply a configuration file or a
            configuration directory, please add this file as an explicit input to the component.
            Other options include, e.g., fixing a "whitelist" of safe configuration options and
            allowing the user a choice of these configuration options via properties.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Groups</title>
        <para>With groups you can categorize the properties and group properties for the same
            context. It is also possible to create a file for each group at runtime, which contains
            the keys and the respective values. These files will be located in the “Config” folder
            in a temporary directory with the name that you can also define here.</para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
