<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>Database Component Usage</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para> With the database component databases can be accessed. Database management is not the
            focus of this component.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Rationale</title>
        <para>The database component executes one or more SQL statements and can write the result of
            each statement into one output if specified.</para>
        <para>The statement can be composed using placeholders for inputs configured in the
            component (see "Inputs/Outputs").</para>
        <para>Currently supported statement types are SELECT, INSERT, UPDATE, DELETE. Management
            tasks, like creating users and handling their privileges as well as altering the
            database structure are not the purpose of the component.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Defining a database connection</title>
            <para>In the properties view of the database component there is a <emphasis
                    role="italic">"Database"</emphasis> tab. Here you can define the database
                connection this component works on. Note that currently drivers for MySQL and
                PostgreSQL databases are supported. The credentials required to access the database
                can be entered later on when you execute the workflow.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Use the credentials</title>
            <para>When you execute a workflow that contains a database component you are asked for
                the username and password. Note that you can store the password in an encrypted
                storage if you check the "save" check box.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Using your own connectors</title>
            <para>As default a MySQL JDBC connector in version 5.1.17 is used and already shipped
                with your RCE installation. You can find it in the subfolder
                ".../extras/database_connectors" in your RCE installation folder. If you want to use
                your own connector simply replace the connector file. It will automatically be
                loaded when you restart RCE. As mentioned above: Only drivers for MySQL and
                PostgreSQL database are supported currently. If you require a different driver class
                feel free to contact us.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Database statements</title>
            <para>For each database component you can enter multiple statements. They are defined in
                the "Statement" tab. Pressing the "&lt; + &gt;" tab will open a new statement tab.
                Every tab must not contain more than one statement. For every statement you can
                define whether its result should be written to an output. To dynamically compose
                database statements by using placeholders for inputs you can make use of the "Input"
                group. A placeholder is added at the current caret position which will be replaced
                by the actual input value at runtime. Likewise the "Templates" group will insert
                templates for the given statement types which you can edit to fit your
                purpose.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Writing multiple times to the same output</title>
            <para>It is possible to configure multiple statements to write their result sets to the
                same output. The results are queued. Note that this can cause subsequent components
                to run multiple times to consume the queued values. Moreover subsequent must allow
                queuing of input values.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Output "success"</title>
            <para>There is a static output of type boolean named <emphasis role="italic"
                    >"success"</emphasis>. It is set to <emphasis role="italic">true</emphasis> if
                the given statement and result set distribution was successful. It is useful when a
                database statement does not yield a result set (like an INSERT statement, for
                instance) but should trigger the start of a succeeding component. If there are
                multiple statements defined in a component instance then the "success" output is
                written when all statements have been processed.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Valid statement types</title>
            <para>The database component is designed to query and update databases on a lightweight
                basis. As already mentioned above typical database management statements like
                creating, altering and dropping tables or working on views and user account is not
                the aim of this component. Thus, the following four database statement types are
                supported. That means, each statement must begin with one of the following
                phrases:</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>SELECT</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>INSERT</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>UPDATE</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>DELETE</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Handling Small Tables</title>
            <para>Inputs of type "Small Table" can only be used in INSERT statements.</para>
            <para>Example:</para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>INSERT INTO table_name (id, col1, col2, col3) VALUES ${in:mySmallTable}</programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>Outputs of type "Small Table" are filled by converting the result set from the
                database to RCE's data types. Note that small tables cannot be encapsulated in small
                tables.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Handling Result Sets</title>
            <para>If a result set is empty but configured to be written to an output, this is
                interpreted as an error.</para>
            <para>If a result set has exactly one row and one column, it is tried to be mapped to
                the respective RCE data type.</para>
            <para>If a result set has more than one entry and the respective output channel is small
                table a mapping is executed.</para>
            <para>If the respective output channel is boolean, short text, integer or float but the
                result set has more than one entry this is interpreted as a potential erroneous
                configuration and causes the component to fail.</para>
            <para>If values in the result set are mapped to Java's data type "Big Decimal" it cannot
                be processed as there is currently no data type of RCE that can represent it.</para>
            <para>If values in the result set are mapped to Java's data type Timestamp it cannot be
                processed as there is currently no data type of RCE that can represent it. As a
                workaround you can cast or transfer the timestamp to some textual representation
                with SQL functionalities and work on with this.</para>
            <para>If values in the result set are null it is mapped to RCE's data type "Empty" has
                the textual representation <emphasis role="italic">"nil"</emphasis>.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Local Execution Only</title>
            <para>Please note that the database component cannot be published and remotely used. To
                use the database in your local workflow make sure you can access the database from
                your machine and configure the database component accordingly.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Examples</title>
        <para>The following examples refer to the "world" example which can be found at the mysql
            website: <ulink url="https://dev.mysql.com/doc/index-other.html"
                >https://dev.mysql.com/doc/index-other.html</ulink></para>
        <para>The following list gives examples for the statement types without inputs configured in
            the component:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                        <programlisting>SELECT * FROM City;</programlisting>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                        <programlisting>DELETE FROM City WHERE ID = 3076;</programlisting>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                        <programlisting>UPDATE City SET Population = 1000000 WHERE ID = 3071;</programlisting>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                        <programlisting>INSERT INTO City (ID, Name, CountryCode, District, Population) VALUES (4080, 'Cochem', 'DEU', 'Rheinland-Pfalz', 5213);</programlisting>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>The following examples demonstrate the usage of inputs configured in the
            component:</para>
        <para> <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                    <programlisting>SELECT * FROM City WHERE ID = ${in:id};</programlisting>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                    <programlisting>DELETE FROM City WHERE ID = ${in:id}; </programlisting>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                    <programlisting>UPDATE City SET Population = ${in:population} WHERE ID = ${in:id};</programlisting>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                    <programlisting>INSERT INTO City (ID, Name, CountryCode, District, Population) VALUES(${in:id}, ${in:name}, ${in:code}, ${in:district}, ${in:population});</programlisting>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>Considering inputs of type small table, the example above in the context of the world
            database would look as follows, assumed the input is properly
            defined:<programlisting>INSERT INTO City (ID, Name, CountryCode, District, Population) VALUES ${in:smallTable};</programlisting></para>
        <para>For further information you may want to refer to the MySQL documentation: <ulink
                url="https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.7/en/sql-syntax.html"
                >https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.7/en/sql-syntax.html</ulink></para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
