<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="tool_integration">
    <title>Integration of External Tools</title>
    <sect2>
        <title>Basic Concepts</title>
        <para>The Tool Integration concept of RCE is used to integrate external tools for
            calculations, simulations and so on into RCE and use them in a workflow as a component.
            The tools must fulfill these requirements:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The external tool must be callable via command line</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>It must have a non-interactive mode which is called via command line</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Input for the tool must be provided through command line arguments or
                    files</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>If these requirements are fulfilled, a configuration file can be created that is used
            for the integration. </para>
        <para>If you use RCE with a graphical user interface this can be done with the help of an
            wizard which guides you through the settings. This wizard can be found in the menu
                <emphasis role="italic">Tool Integration -> Integrate Tool...</emphasis>. Required
            fields are marked with an asterisk (*). When the wizard is finished and everything is
            correct, the integrated tool will automatically show up in the Workflow Editor
            palette.</para>
        <para>
            <note>
                <para>The wizard has a dynamic help, which is shown by clicking on the question mark
                    on the bottom left or by pressing F1. It will guide you through every page of
                    the wizard.</para>
            </note>
        </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
        <title>Directory Structure for Integrated Tools</title>
        <para>When executing an integrated tool, a certain directory structure is created in the
            chosen working directory. This structure depends on the options you have chosen in the
            integration wizard. The two options that matter are "Use a new working directory each
            run" and "Tool copying behavior".</para>
        <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/Folderstructure.png" width="400px"/></para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Root Working Directory</emphasis>: This is the directory you
            choose in the "Tool Integration Wizard" as "Working Directory" on the "Launch Settings"
            page.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Config Directory</emphasis>: In this directory, the
            configuration file that may be created by the tool integration will be created by
            default. The configuration files can be created from the properties that are defined for
            the tool on the "Tool Properties" page.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Input Directory</emphasis>: All inputs of type "File" and
            "Directory" will be copied here. They will have a subdirectory that is named exactly as
            the input's name (e.g. the input "x" of type "File" will be put into "Input
            Directory/x/filename").</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Output Directory</emphasis>: All outputs of type "File" and
            "Directory" can be written into this directory. After that, you can use the placeholder
            for this directory to assign these outputs to RCE outputs in the post execution script.
            To write the output directory into an output "x" of type "Directory" the following line
            in the post execution script would be required: ${out:x} = "${dir:output}"</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Tool Directory</emphasis>: This is the directory, where the
            actual tool is located. If the tool should not be copied, it will be exactly the same
            directory that you choose, otherwise it will be the same as the chosen directory but
            copied to the working directory.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Working Directory</emphasis>: A working directory is always the
            location, where all the other directories will be created. If the option "Use a new
            working directory on each run" is disabled, this will always be the same as the "Root
            Working Directory". Otherwise, a new directory is created each run (the name will be the
            run number) and is the working directory for the run.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
        <title>Copying of Integrated Tools</title>
        <para>When a component is created in the integration wizard, a configuration file is
            created.</para>
        <para>All configuration files from the tool integration are stored in the directory</para>
        <para><code>&lt;profile folder>/integration/tools/</code></para>
        <para>In this directory, there is a separation between different kinds of integration
            realized through one subdirectory for each. The <code>common</code> folder is always
            existent.</para>
        <para>In these subdirectory, the integrated tools are stored, again separated through a
            subdirectory for each. The name of the directory equals the name of integration of the
            tool. </para>
        <para>If an integrated tool should be copied to another RCE instance or another machine, the
            directory of the tool must be copied, containing a <code>configuration.json</code> and
            some optional files. It must be put in the equivalent integration type directory of the
            target RCE instance. After that, RCE automatically reads the new folder and if
            everything is valid, the tool will be integrated right away.</para>
        <para>
            <note>
                <para>If you want to delete a tool folder that contains some documentation, this can
                    cause an error. If you have this problem, delete the documentation folder at
                    first (it must be empty), afterwards you can delete the tool folder.</para>
            </note>
        </para>
        <sect3>
            <title>Tool Execution Return Codes</title>
            <para>The tools are executed by using a command line call on the operating system via
                the "Execution Script". When the tool finished executing (with or without error),
                its exit code is handed back to the execution script and can be analyzed in this
                script. If in the script nothing else is done, the exit code is handed back to RCE.
                When there is an exit code that is not "0", RCE assumes that the tool crashed and
                thus lets the component crash without executing the "Post Script". Using the option
                "Exit codes other than 0 is not an error" can prevent the component to crash
                immediately. With this option enabled, the post script wil be executed in any way
                and the exit code from the tool execution can be read by using the placeholder from "Additional
                Properties". In this case, the post script can run any post processing and either
                not fail the component, so the workflow runs as normal, or let the compoennt crash
                after some debugging information was written using the Script API
                "RCE.fail("reason")".</para>
            <para/>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
        <title>Integration of CPACS Tools</title>
        <sect3>
            <title>Additional concepts of CPACS Tool Integration</title>
            <para>Extending the common Tool Integration concept, the CPACS Tool Integration has some
                additional features.<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Parameter Input Mapping (optional): Substitutes single values in the
                            incoming CPACS content, based on an XPath configured at workflow design
                            time as a dynamic input of the component</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Input Mapping: Generates the tool input XML file as a subset of the
                            incoming CPACS file XML structure, specified by a mapping file </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Tool Specific Input Mapping (optional): Adds tool specific data to the
                            tool input file, based on a mapping file and a data XML file</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Output Mapping: Merges the content of the tool output XML file into
                            the origin incoming CPACS file, based on a mapping file</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Parameter Output Mapping (optional): Generates output values as single
                            values of the CPACS result file, based on an XPath configured at
                            workflow design time as a dynamic output of the component</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Execution option to only run on changed input: If enabled, the
                            integrated tool will only run on changed input. Therefore the content of
                            the generated tool input file is compared to the last runs content.
                            Additionally the data of the static input channels are compared to the
                            previous ones.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <para>All the features listed above can be configured in the tool integration wizard on
                the dedicated <emphasis role="italic">CPACS Tool Properties</emphasis> page.</para>
            <para>The mappings can be specified by XML or XSLT as shown in the following examples.
                RCE differentiates between these methods in accordance to the corresponding file
                extension (.xml or .xsl).</para>
            <para>Example for an input or tool specific XML mapping :</para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
&lt;map:mappings xmlns:map="http://www.rcenvironment.de/2015/mapping" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform">

    &lt;map:mapping>
        &lt;map:source>/cpacs/vehicles/aircraft/model/reference/area&lt;/map:source>
        &lt;map:target>/toolInput/data/var1&lt;/map:target>
    &lt;/map:mapping>

&lt;/map:mappings></programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>And input or tool specific XSLT mapping:</para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
&lt;xsl:stylesheet version="1.0" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="cpacs_schema.xsd">
 &lt;xsl:output method="xml" media-type="text/xml" />
 &lt;xsl:template match="/">
  &lt;toolInput>
   &lt;data>
    &lt;var1>
     &lt;xsl:value-of select="/cpacs/vehicles/aircraft/model/reference/area" />
    &lt;/var1>
   &lt;/data>
  &lt;/toolInput>
 &lt;/xsl:template>
&lt;/xsl:stylesheet></programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>Example of an output XML mapping:</para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
&lt;map:mappings xmlns:map="http://www.rcenvironment.de/2015/mapping" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform">

    &lt;map:mapping mode="delete">
        &lt;map:source>/toolOutput/data/result1&lt;/map:source>
        &lt;map:target>/cpacs/vehicles/aircraft/model/reference/area&lt;/map:target>
    &lt;/map:mapping>

&lt;/map:mappings></programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>And output XSLT mapping:</para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
&lt;xsl:stylesheet version="1.0" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" exclude-result-prefixes="xsi">
  &lt;xsl:output method="xml" version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" indent="yes"/>
  &lt;!--Define Variable for toolOutput.xml-->
  &lt;xsl:variable name="toolOutputFile" select="'./ToolOutput/toolOutput.xml'"/>
  &lt;!--Copy complete Source (e.g. CPACSInitial.xml) to Result (e.g. CPACSResult.xml)-->
  &lt;xsl:template match="@* | node()">
    &lt;xsl:copy>
      &lt;xsl:apply-templates select="@* | node()"/>
    &lt;/xsl:copy>
  &lt;/xsl:template>
  &lt;!--Modify a value of an existing node-->
    &lt;xsl:template match="/cpacs/vehicles/aircraft/model/reference/area">
    &lt;area>  
    &lt;xsl:value-of select="document($toolOutputFile)/toolOutput/data/result1"/>
    &lt;/area>
    &lt;/xsl:template>
&lt;/xsl:stylesheet></programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>Please ensure to use the proper namespace for map
                (xmlns:map="http://www.rcenvironment.de/2015/mapping") in XML mapping files.</para>
            <para>The figure below illustrates how the additional features are used in the run
                process of an user-integrated CPACS tool.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Run process of an user-integrated CPACS Tool</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/ug_CPACS_ToolRunProcess.png"
                        contentwidth="390"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
            <title>Integrate a CPACS Tool into a Client Instance</title>
        
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Start RCE as Client</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Open the <emphasis role="italic">Tool Integration Wizard</emphasis> by
                            clicking the <emphasis role="italic">Integrate Tool...</emphasis> in the
                                <emphasis role="italic">File</emphasis> menu.<note>
                                <para>You will always find further help by clicking the <emphasis
                                        role="italic">?</emphasis> on the bottom left corner on each
                                    page of the wizard or by pressing <emphasis role="italic"
                                        >F1</emphasis>.</para>
                            </note>
                        </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Choose the option <emphasis role="italic">Create a new tool configuration
                                from a template</emphasis>. <note>
                                <para>The CPACS templates delivered with RCE are designed to match
                                    the conventions of the old CPACS tool wrapper (respectively
                                    ModelCenter tool wrapper). Most of the properties are
                                    preconfigured and do not need to be changed.</para>
                            </note></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Select one of the <emphasis role="italic">CPACS</emphasis> templates.
                            <?linebreak?>Click <emphasis role="italic">Next</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Fill in the <emphasis role="italic">Tool Description</emphasis> page.
                            <?linebreak?>Click <emphasis role="italic">Next</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>On the <emphasis role="italic">Inputs and Outputs</emphasis> page you will
                            find preconfigured static in- and outputs, that will match the old tool
                            wrapper conventions. If your tool needs additional in- or outputs, feel
                            free to configure.<?linebreak?>Click <emphasis role="italic">Next</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Skip the page<emphasis role="italic"> Tool Properties</emphasis> by
                            clicking <emphasis role="italic">Next</emphasis> since it is not
                            relevant for tools that match the conventions of the old CPACS tool
                            wrapper.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Add a launch setting for the tool by clicking the <emphasis role="italic"
                                >Add</emphasis> button on the <emphasis role="italic">Launch
                                Settings</emphasis> page. Configure the path of the CPACS tool and
                            fill in a version, click <emphasis role="italic">OK</emphasis>. If you
                            would like to allow users of your tool to choose that the temp directory
                            won’t be deleted at all after workflow execution, check the property
                                <emphasis role="italic">Never delete working
                                directory(ies)</emphasis>. Not to delete the working directory can
                            be very useful for users for debugging purposes, at least if they have
                            access to the server’s file system. But this option can result in disc
                            space issues as the amount required grows continuously with each
                            workflow execution. It is recommended to check that option during
                            integrating the tool and uncheck it before publishing the tool.
                            <?linebreak?>Click <emphasis role="italic">Next</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The <emphasis role="italic">CPACS Tool Properties</emphasis> are
                            preconfigured to match the folder structure defined for the old CPACS
                            tool wrapper. In most cases you do not have to change this
                            configuration. If you are using XSLT mapping, please select the
                            corresponding mapping files. If your tool does not work with static tool
                            specific input, please deselect this property. <?linebreak?>Click
                                <emphasis role="italic">Next</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the <emphasis role="italic">Execution command(s)</emphasis> tab on the
                                <emphasis role="italic">Execution</emphasis> page, you need to
                            define your execution command itself as well as optional pre and post
                            commands. Commands will be processed sequentially line by line. An
                            example for a typical Windows command including pre and post commands
                            will look like the following:</para>
                    <para>
                        <programlisting>rem pre-command
pre.bat

rem tool-execution
YourTool.exe ToolInput/toolInput.xml ToolOutput/toolOutput.xml

rem post-command
post.bat</programlisting>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Click <emphasis role="italic">Save and activate</emphasis> and your tool
                            will appear immediately in the palette and is be ready to use.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If not already done, do not forget to publish your tool (cf. Section<xref
                                linkend="publishing_authorization"/> ) after testing it locally. To
                            check if your tool is successfully published to the RCE network open the
                            tab <emphasis role="italic">Network View</emphasis> at the bottom and
                            checkout <emphasis role="italic">Published Components</emphasis> after
                            expanding the entry of your RCE instance.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
            <title>Integrate a CPACS Tool into a Server Instance in Headless Mode</title>
            <para>The way to integrate a CPACS tool on a server running RCE in headless mode is as
                follows: Perform the steps to integrate a CPACS tool on a client instance and make
                sure that the path of the CPACS tool configured on the <emphasis role="italic">Launch Settings</emphasis> page (step 8) matches the absolute tool path on your
                server system. Afterwards, you will find the configuration files inside your rce
                profile folder at the following location:</para>
            <para><code>/integration/tools/cpacs/[YourToolName]</code></para>
            <para>Copy the folder <code>[YourToolName]</code> to the same location inside the
                profile folder running with your headless server instance. Use the "auth" commands
                (cf. Section<xref linkend="publishing_authorization"/> ) to publish your tool. If
                the server instance is already running, your tool will be available immediately
                after publishing.</para>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>
    
</sect1>
