<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>XML Merger Component Usage</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>The XML Merger component merges the XML content of two inputs on the basis of
            user-defined rules. These rules can be described in the XML or the XLST format and can
            either be sent to the component as an input file or can be configured in the component's
            properties view.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Rationale</title>
        <para>The basic functionality of the XML Merger component is to merge two XML data sets into
            one as follows: There is a 'main'-XML data set (input channel "XML"). The complete XSLT
            mapping will be described regarding this XML dataset. All integrating parts of another
            XML data set (input channel "XML to integrate") will be described with a
            'document'-reference in XSLT mapping.</para>
        <para>As XSLT is a standard technology in the field of information technology it is referred
            to corresponding literature available. As a technical background, the approach used is
            based on Saxon processor. In the mapping file (see example) a XSLT-constant
            INTEGRATING_INPUT refers to the XML to integrate data channel.</para>
        <para>Example: XSLT
            mapping:<programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
&lt;xsl:stylesheet version="1.0"
    xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
        xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" exclude-result-prefixes="xsi">

    &lt;xsl:output method="xml" version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" indent="yes"/>

    &lt;!--Define Variable for integrated CPACS-->
    &lt;xsl:variable name="cpacsIntegratedDoc" select="'INTEGRATING_INPUT'"/>

    &lt;!--Copy complete Source to Result -->
    &lt;xsl:template match="@* | node()">
        &lt;xsl:copy>
            &lt;xsl:apply-templates select="@* | node()"/>
        &lt;/xsl:copy>
    &lt;/xsl:template>
    &lt;xsl:template match="/cpacs/aircraft/configuration/trajectories/global">
        &lt;global>
            &lt;ReferenceTrajectoryUID>
                &lt;xsl:value-of select="document($cpacsIntegratedDoc)/cpacs/aircraft/configuration/trajectories/global/ReferenceTrajectoryUID"/>
            &lt;/ReferenceTrajectoryUID>
            &lt;xsl:copy-of select="document($cpacsIntegratedDoc)/cpacs/aircraft/configuration/trajectories/global/ReferenceTrajectory"/>
            &lt;xsl:copy-of select="/cpacs/aircraft/configuration/trajectories/global/*"/>
        &lt;/global>
    &lt;/xsl:template>
&lt;/xsl:stylesheet></programlisting></para>
        <para>Instead of using XSLT, the mapping rules can also be described in XML. </para>
        <para>Example: XML
            mapping:<programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

&lt;map:mappings xmlns:map="http://www.rcenvironment.de/2015/mapping" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform">

	&lt;map:mapping>
	    &lt;map:source>/cpacs/vehicles/aircraft/model/reference/area&lt;/map:source>
	    &lt;map:target>/toolInput/data/var1&lt;/map:target>
	&lt;/map:mapping>
	&lt;map:mapping mode="delete">
           &lt;map:source>/toolOutput/data/result1&lt;/map:source>
           &lt;map:target>/cpacs/vehicles/aircraft/model/reference/area&lt;/map:target>
       &lt;/map:mapping>
	
&lt;/map:mappings>
</programlisting></para>
        <para>
            RCE automatically determines which format is used based on the filename endings, so the 
            mapping file name must end with ".xslt" or ".xml", respectively. 
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>On the “Mapping” tab you can choose whether you want to send the mapping file to the
            XML Merger component via an input (in this case, the component has an input "Mapping
            file", to which the file has to be sent during the workflow) or if you want to load a
            mapping file into the component. In the second case, the content of the mapping file
            will be stored within the workflow, which will lead to a larger workflow file. Editing
            the mapping content allows you to edit and store the corresponding content in the
            workflow (the originally loaded file itself will not be changed).</para>
        <para>You can define the scheduling of the static input channels on the tab
            “Inputs/Outputs”. You are also able to add dynamic input or output channels here. Thus
            it is possible to map single values into the XML dataset via XPATH declaration.
            Moreover, you can select single values in order to write them in an output
            channel.</para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
