<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>Workflow Editor</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>The Workflow Editor is the main view where you can define your workflow logic by
            adding components and connecting them.</para>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Options</title>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Snap to geometry</emphasis>: Components and labels
                        snap to each other when the toolbar entry "Snap to geometry" is activated.
                        Again, pressing "Alt" while dragging omits the snapping.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Fore- and background</emphasis>: You can send
                        components and labels to back- or foreground using the context menu entries
                        "Send Back", "Send Forward", "Send to Background" and "Send to Foreground".
                        While the first two entries change the layer by one, the latter two put it
                        to the front or to the back. Note that workflow components and labels are
                        treated separately, i.e. components are always in front of labels.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Number of connections</emphasis>: The number of
                        connections bundled within a single arrow can be shown. To see it either
                        select a connection or select the toolbar entry "Show number of connections
                        in workflow editor".</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Custom connection paths</emphasis>: They can be
                        defined by selecting a connection and dragging the dot. You can reset the
                        custom connection path in the context menu of the connection by clicking the
                        entry "Reset Connection Path". Ctrl + Delete is the shortcut for resetting
                        the connection path. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Disable/Enable workflow components</emphasis>: In a
                        component's context menu you can disable components so they are ignored when
                        you execute the workflow. That can be useful when you are in the process of
                        creating the workflow and temporarily just want to execute a part of the
                        workflow. Disabled components are greyed out.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Disable/Enable tool run imitation mode</emphasis>:
                        User integrated tools can be configured to support a tool run imitation
                        mode. This can be useful if you want to get your workflow logic straight but
                        don't want to run the actual tool every time. In the context menu of an
                        integrated component you can enable or diabled this mode. If the tool run
                        imitation mode is enabled the component appears in blue and has an "I" for
                        "Imitation" at the bottom right edge.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Open documentation:</emphasis> User integrated tools
                        can be configured to have a text or PDF file as documentation. If there is
                        such a documentation the context menu entry "Open documentation" will open
                        it in an editor, otherwise a message is shown.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Undo/Redo</emphasis>: You can undo and redo actions
                        in the workflow editor. It is restricted to 10 actions for technical
                        reasons.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>Note that there is also a <emphasis role="bold">read-only</emphasis> pendant of the
            Workflow Editor, where you can inspect a workflow without editing it. Workflows opened
            from the Workflow Data Browser get displayed this way. Additionally, Workflows can also
            be opened read-only from the Project Explorer by selecting "Open With"->"Read-only
            Workflow Editor".</para>
        <para/>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
