<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="configuration">
	<title>Configuration</title>
	<para>This section describes the configuration of RCE. Configuration is done within one single
		configuration file. It is located in the profile directory. From the graphical user
		interface, you can easily access it from the tool bar or <emphasis role="italic"
			>Help</emphasis> menu. Note: To apply changes you need to restart RCE. The format of the
		configuration file is JSON. See <ulink url="http://www.json.org/"><emphasis role="underline"
				>http://www.json.org/</emphasis></ulink> for the format definition. Also refer to
		the example configuration files in the installation data directory.</para>
	<sect2>
		<title>Configuration Locations and Files</title>
		<para>Starting with RCE 6.0.0, all user data is strictly separated from the RCE installation
			itself. Each set of user data is contained in a so-called "profile". Each profile
			defines what is called an RCE "instance". Each profile (and therefore, each instance)
			belongs to exactly one user, and each user can have multiple profiles. The default
			profile is located within the user's "home" directory (<phrase os="windows"
				>"C:\users\&lt;user id>\" on Windows</phrase><phrase os="linux">"/home/&lt;user
					id>/" on Linux</phrase>), in the ".rce/default" sub-folder.<note>
						<para>Note that ".rce" is a hidden directory; you may need to set operating-specific
							options to see hidden files and directories.</para>
					</note></para>
		<para>All manual configuration takes place in the profile's central configuration file,
			"configuration.json". As of RCE 6.0.0, most configuration settings only take effect on
			startup, so you need to restart RCE after editing it. (This will be changed in an future
			release.) This applies to all types of installations.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>Configuration Parameters</title>
		<para>Configuration parameters are grouped within the configuration file. Below are lists of the
			configuration parameters. There is one list per group.</para>
		<table width="100%">
			<title>general</title>
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2*"/>
				<colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry><emphasis role="italic">Configuration key </emphasis></entry>
						<entry>
							<emphasis role="italic">Comment </emphasis></entry>
						<entry>
							<emphasis role="italic">Default value </emphasis></entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
			<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>instanceName</entry>
						<entry>The name of the instance that will be shown to all users in the RCE network.</entry>
						<entry>"&lt;unnamed instance>"</entry>
					</row>
				<row>
					<entry>isWorkflowHost </entry>
					<entry>If set to <emphasis role="italic">true</emphasis>, the local instance can be used as a
								<emphasis role="italic">workflow host</emphasis> by other RCE
							instances. I.e., the workflow controller can be set to this instance and
							the workflow data is stored there as well.</entry>
					<entry>false</entry>
				</row>
					<row>
						<entry>isRelay</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>If set to <emphasis>true</emphasis>, the local node will merge all
								connected nodes into a single network, and forward messages between
								them. This behaviour is transitive; if a relay node connects to
								another relay node, both networks will effectively merge into
								one.</para>
							<para>If set to <emphasis>false</emphasis> (the default value), the
								local node can connect to multiple networks at once without causing
								them to merge.</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>false</entry>
					</row>
				<row>
					<entry>tempDirectory </entry>
					<entry>Can be used to override the default path where RCE stores temporary files. Useful if
							there is little space in the default temp file location. Must be an
							absolute path to an existing directory, and the path must not contain
							spaces (to prevent problems with tools accessing such
							directories).</entry>
					<entry>An "rce-temp" subdirectory within the user or system temp directory.</entry>
				</row>
			</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<note>
			<para>IMPORTANT: When setting up a network of RCE instances, keep in mind that the RCE
				network traffic is currently <emphasis>not encrypted</emphasis>. This means that it
				is <emphasis>not secure</emphasis> to expose RCE server ports to untrusted networks
				like the internet. When setting up RCE connections between different locations, make
				sure that they either connect across a secure network (e.g. your institution's
				internal network), or that the connection is secured by other means, like SSH
				tunnelling or a VPN.</para>
		</note>
		<table frame="all" width="100%">
			<title>network</title>
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2*"/>
				<colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry><emphasis role="italic">Configuration key </emphasis></entry>
						<entry>
							<emphasis role="italic">Comment </emphasis></entry>
						<entry>
							<emphasis role="italic">Default value </emphasis></entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>requestTimeoutMsec</entry>
						<entry>The timeout (in milliseconds) for network requests that are made by
							the local node. If this time expires before a response is received, the
							request fails.</entry>
						<entry>40000</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>forwardingTimeout Msec</entry>
						<entry>The timeout (in milliseconds) for network requests that are forwarded
							by the local node on behalf of another node. If this time expires before
							a response is received, an error reponse is sent back to the node that
							made the request.</entry>
						<entry>35000</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>connections</entry>
						<entry>A list of all connections that the local instance tries to establish
							on startup. This allows the local instance to act as a client. For each
							connection a unique identifier (id) must be given.</entry>
						<entry>{} (an empty list in JSON format)</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>connections/[id]/host</entry>
						<entry>IP address of the host to connect to. Host names and IPv4 adresses are
							permitted.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>connections/[id]/port</entry>
						<entry>Port number of the remote RCE instance.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>connections/[id]/connectOnStartup</entry>
						<entry>If set to <emphasis role="italic">true</emphasis>, the connection is immediately
							established on startup.</entry>
						<entry>true</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>connections/[id]/autoRetry InitialDelay</entry>
						<entry>The initial delay, in seconds, to wait after a failed or broken
							connection before a reconnect attempt is made. This configuration must
							be present to enable the auto-reconnect feature.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>connections/[id]/autoRetry DelayMultiplier</entry>
						<entry>A decimal-point value >= 1 that the delay time is multiplied with
							after each consecutive connection failure. This provides an "exponential
							backoff" feature that reduces the frequency of connection attempts over
							time. This configuration must be present to enable the auto-reconnect
							feature.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>connections/[id]/autoRetry MaximumDelay</entry>
						<entry>Defines an upper limit for the delay time, even when applying the
							multiplier would create a higher value. This can be used to maintain a
							minimum frequency for retrying the connection. This configuration must
							be present to enable the auto-reconnect feature.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>serverPorts </entry>
						<entry>A list of all server ports that the local instance registers for other instances to
							connect to. This allows the local instance to act as a server. For each
							server port a unique identifier (id) must be given.</entry>
						<entry>{} (an empty list in JSON format)</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>serverPorts/[id]/ip</entry>
						<entry>IP address to which the local instance should be bound.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>serverPorts/[id]/port</entry>
						<entry>Port number to which other instances connect to.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ipFilter </entry>
						<entry>Allows to limit the incoming connections to a set of IP addresses.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ipFilter/enabled </entry>
						<entry>If set to <emphasis role="italic">true</emphasis>, the ip filter active.</entry>
						<entry>false</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ipFilter/allowedIPs</entry>
						<entry>List of IP addresses, which are allowed to connect to the instance.</entry>
						<entry>[] (an empty list in JSON format)</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
			<table width="100%">
			<title>publishing</title>
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2*"/>
				<colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry><emphasis role="italic">Configuration key </emphasis></entry>
						<entry>
							<emphasis role="italic">Comment </emphasis></entry>
						<entry>
							<emphasis role="italic">Default value </emphasis></entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>components </entry>
						<entry>List of workflow components, which are made available to other instances within the RCE
							network. Workflow components are represented by their identifiers. Note:
							That doesn't affect integrated tools.</entry>
						<entry>[] (an empty list in JSON format)</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
			</table>
		<table width="100%">
			<title>componentSettings</title>
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2*"/>
				<colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry><emphasis role="italic">Configuration key </emphasis></entry>
						<entry>
							<emphasis role="italic">Comment </emphasis></entry>
						<entry>
							<emphasis role="italic">Default value </emphasis></entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>de.rcenvironment.cluster</entry>
						<entry>Configuration of the cluster workflow component.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>de.rcenvironment.cluster/maxChannels</entry>
						<entry>Maximum number of channels, which are allowed to be opened in
							parallel to the cluster server.</entry>
						<entry>8</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>de.rcenvironment.sql</entry>
						<entry>Configuration of the SQLworkflow components.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>de.rcenvironment.sql/profiles </entry>
						<entry>List of profiles which will describe the jdbc connection to a database. All
							configuration keys following are part of one entry of the collection </entry>
						<entry>[] (an empty list in JSON format)</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>de.rcenvironment.sql/label </entry>
						<entry>A name for a profile. This label will be shown in the configuration view of the SQL
							component </entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>de.rcenvironment.sql/host </entry>
						<entry>A url to the host computer of the database </entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>de.rcenvironment.sql/database </entry>
						<entry>The name of the database </entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>de.rcenvironment.sql/user </entry>
						<entry>The username for database access </entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>de.rcenvironment.sql/password </entry>
						<entry>The password of the user for database access </entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>de.rcenvironment.sql/jdbc </entry>
						<entry>List of jdbc configuration parameters. All configuration keys following are part of
							this list </entry>
						<entry>{} (an empty list in JSON format)</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>de.rcenvironment.sql/url </entry>
						<entry>Connection string of jdbc driver. Per default, it will be assembled with configuration
							keys above.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>de.rcenvironment.sql/file </entry>
						<entry>Absolute or relative (beginning at root-folder of RCE) path to jdbc driver file </entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>de.rcenvironment.sql/driver </entry>
						<entry>SQL driver classname </entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
			</table>
			<table width="100%">
			<title>sshServer</title>
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2*"/>
				<colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry><emphasis role="italic">Configuration key </emphasis></entry>
						<entry>
							<emphasis role="italic">Comment </emphasis></entry>
						<entry>
							<emphasis role="italic">Default value </emphasis></entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>enabled</entry>
						<entry>If set to <emphasis role="italic">true</emphasis> the local instance acts as an SSH
							server.</entry>
						<entry>false</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>port</entry>
						<entry>Port number to which SSH clients connect to.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>accounts</entry>
						<entry>List of accounts. For each account a unique identifier (account name) must be
							given.</entry>
						<entry>{} (an empty list in JSON format)</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>[account name]/password</entry>
						<entry>Password for the account.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>[account name]/role</entry>
						<entry>Role of the account. See 'roles' below.</entry>
						<entry>-</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>[account name]/enabled</entry>
						<entry>If set to <emphasis role="italic">true</emphasis>, the account is enabled.</entry>
						<entry>true</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>roles</entry>
						<entry>List of roles. For each role a unique identifier (role name) must be given.</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>[role name]/allowed CommandPatterns</entry>
						<entry>List of commands the role is allowed to execute. Regular expressions
							are supported.</entry>
						<entry>[] (an empty list in JSON format)</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
			</table>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
