<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>Palette View Usage</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>The Palette view displays all the local and currently available remote workflow
            components of the current RCE instance in a tree structure.</para>
        <para>By default, workflow components are grouped as defined by their respective integrator.
            In addition to the standard grouping, however, workflow components can be moved into
            custom groups. For this purpose, custom groups and subgroups can be added, edited or
            deleted. The workflow components can always be reset to their respective standard
            group.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>By default, components are assigned to one of the following top level groups, depending
            on their type:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Standard Components: Built-in components provided by RCE supplying multi-purpose
            functionalities (see User Guide; Section 3.2.3 Workflow Components).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>User Integrated Tools: Software tools or scripts that are integrated into RCE
                    using the "Tool Integration" feature and then represent a workflow component
                    (see User Guide; Section 3.4.1 Integrating External Tools as Components).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>User Integrated Workflows: RCE workflows consisting of several workflow
                    components that are themselves integrated as a component using the "Workflow as
                    Component" feature (see User Guide; Section 3.4.2 Integrating Workflows as
                    Components).</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Toolbar items allow to filter the tree by components, sort groups and collapse and
            expand all groups.</para>
        <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image001.PNG"/></para>
        <para>Workflow components can be moved into user-defined groups. These custom groups are
            indicated by a small decorator <inlinegraphic
                fileref="../../images/decorator_custom.png"/> overlaying the folder icon. Custom
            groups can be added, edited and deleted via the context menu or the "Manage Custom
            Groups" dialog. This dialog can also be accessed via the context menu of the Palette
            view as well as via the main menu (Configuration -> Custom Palette Groups) or the main
            toolbar. </para>
        <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image002.PNG"/></para>
        <para>It is not possible to add custom groups to the top level group "Standard Components"
            as this subgroup structure is predefined by RCE. However, custom top level groups can be
            added and different types of workflow components can be moved into them.</para>
        <para>All integrated tools are assigned to a default group. If no default group is defined,
            the tool is subordinated to the top level "User Integrated Tools". Other integrated
            tools can be moved here but these groups will not be changed to a custom group. Since
            these are default groups, they can neither be empty nor renamed. If all tools are
            removed from a default group, this group disappears from the view. However, after
            resetting a tool, the group will be visible again.</para>
        <para>Moving components or resetting them to their default group is also possible via the
            context menu. In addition, the tool documentation can be opend or exported from here and
            the edit tool dialog as well as the tool integration and deactivation dialog can be
            accessed.</para>
        <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image003.PNG"/></para>
        <para>The "Manage Custom Groups" dialog shows all custom group assignments of local and
            remote components regardless of whether or not they are currently available in the
            network. This means that custom group assignments of components that are not available
            can also be reset via this dialog. In this table, multiple entries can be selected at
            the same time via Ctrl or Shift in order to reset components or delete groups. <note>
                <para>Unavailable remote components are not visible in the Palette view and can only
                    be reset via the "Manage Custom Groups" dialog.</para>
                <para>A custom group can only be deleted if it is empty. This prevents the deletion
                    of groups with remote assignments that are currently unavailable.</para>
            </note></para>
        <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image004.PNG"/></para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
