<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>XML Loader Component Usage</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>The XML Loader component loads an XML file from a project within the workspace into
            the workflow.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>In the 'File' tab you can load an XML file into the component by clicking on the
            "Load... " button and navigating to the file of your choice. The content of the XML file
            will be stored within the workflow and is shown in the text box below so you can quickly
            verify that you chose the correct file:<note>Changing the file itself does not change
                the loaded content. You have to load the file again to apply changes.</note></para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Writing values into an XML file</title>
        <para>To map single values into the XML dataset you have to add one input channel per value
            to be mapped. If you require more complex or conditional mappings or transformations please refer to the XML Merger component. In the "Add Input" dialog click "XPath choosing... " and  navigate to an
            XML file with the same structure as the one you referenced in the 'File' tab, preferably
            the same file. In the appearing "XPath Variables Dialog" window navigate along the tree
            to the node you desire to change and drag it to the "Variables" section below. When the
            component is executed the value being received on this input channel will be written to
            the XPath location defined here. The resulting XML file with the inserted values is written to the output "XML". You can check the original and the outgoing XML files in the workflow data browser.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Reading values from an XML file</title>
        <para>
            To read single values from an XML file add a dynamic output. In the "Add Output" dialog click "XPath choosing... " and  navigate to an
            XML file with the same structure as the one you referenced in the 'File' tab, preferably
            the same file. In the appearing "XPath Variables Dialog" window navigate along the tree
            to the node you desire to read and drag it to the "Variables" section below. When the component is executed the content of the node that the XPath points to is written into the output channel.
        </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
