<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="network">
	<title>Connecting RCE instances via the RCE network or via SSH connections</title>
	<para>RCE provides two possibilities to connect your RCE instance to other RCE instances and to use
		the user-integrated tools and components published on those instances: The RCE network
		connections and SSH connections. RCE connections are meant to be used only in a trusted
		network (e.g. your institution's internal network). The RCE network traffic is currently
			<emphasis>not encrypted</emphasis>. This means that it is <emphasis>not
			secure</emphasis> to expose RCE server ports to untrusted networks like the internet. In
		the case that it is not possible or not secure to use RCE connections, SSH connections
		provide a more secure alternative. However, not all tools can be used via an SSH connection
		in the current version. The following table compares the two connection types:<table
			frame="all">
			<title>Connection types</title>
			<tgroup cols="6">
				<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.06*"/>
				<colspec colname="newCol4" colnum="2" colwidth="1.7*"/>
				<colspec colname="newCol9" colnum="3" colwidth="2.55*"/>
				<colspec colname="newCol6" colnum="4" colwidth="1.67*"/>
				<colspec colname="newCol7" colnum="5" colwidth="1.98*"/>
				<colspec colname="c2" colnum="6" colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Connection type</entry>
						<entry>Access to all published tools</entry>
						<entry>Supporting all RCE network functions (e.g. tool documentation, remote
							monitoring...)</entry>
						<entry>Encrypted traffic</entry>
						<entry>Using login name and password or RSA key</entry>
						<entry>Symmetrical</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>RCE connections</entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">yes</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">yes</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">no</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">no</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">yes</emphasis></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>SSH connections</entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">no</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">no</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">yes</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">yes</emphasis></entry>
						<entry><emphasis role="bold">no</emphasis></entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table></para>
	<sect2>
		<title>RCE Network Connections</title>
		<para>RCE connections are meant to be used only in a trusted network (e.g. your
			institution's internal network). To build up a network of RCE instances, at least one of
			the instances has to be configured as a server (see the "Configuration" section or the
			sample configuration file "Relay server" for details).</para>
		<para>On the client side, RCE network connections can be added in the "network" view by clicking
			"Add network connection" and entering the hostname and port of an RCE server instance.
			The connections are shown in the "RCE Network"->"Connections" subtree. They can also be
			edited, connected and disconnected in the network view. However, the changes made here
			are not saved in the configuration yet, i.e. they will be lost when RCE is closed or
			restarted. To permanently add connections, you can edit the configuration file (see the
			"Configuration" section for details). </para>
		<para>In the "RCE Network" -> "Instances" subtree all RCE instances in the network are
			listed. When expanding the entry for an instance, you can see monitoring data like CPU
			or RAM usage for this instance, and the published components and tools of this instance
			(if it has any).</para>
		<para>The published components and tools of the other instances in your network are also shown in
			the palette of the Workflow Editor. From there, you can use them in your workflows just
			like your local components and tools. When you start a workflow, in the "Execute
			Workflow" wizard there is an overview which component will be run on which RCE instance.
			If a component is available on several instances, you can choose here on which instance
			it should be run. In the same wizard, you can also choose another instance as the
			"Controller Target Instance", which means that the workflow execution will be controlled
			by this instance (see the section "Configuration Parameters" for more information). This
			can be useful when you start a long-running workflow where all components are run on
			remote instances and you do not want to keep your local computer connected all the
			time.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>SSH Remote Access Connections</title>
		<para>SSH connections provide a more secure alternative to the standard RCE connections and can be
			used to access tools remotely that were integrated using the "Remote Tool Access"
			template, which determines certain inputs and outputs. The published tools meeting the
			requirements of the "Remote Tool Access" template are shown in the palette of the
			client's Workflow Editor in the group "SSH Remote Access Tools" (this may take a few
			seconds after connecting, as the tool list is fetched from the remote hosts every few
			seconds). From there, you can use them in your workflows just like your local components
			and tools. Differently from tools accessed by RCE network connections, in this case the
			component is shown to be executed on your local instance in the Workflow Execution
			wizard.</para>
		<para>Also workflows that were published on the remote instance (for information about the
			publishing see section "Remote Tool and Workflow Access") are shown as components in the
			palette of the client's Workflow Editor in the group "SSH Remote Access Workflows" (if
			the client runs RCE 7.1 or newer). These remote workflows can be added to workflows and
			executed like local components/tools.</para>
		<sect3>
			<title>Configuring an RCE instance as an SSH server</title>
			<para>The RCE instance that publishes the tool, or another instance connected to it by
				RCE network connections, has to be configured as an RCE remote access server (see
				the "Configuration" section or the sample configuration file "Remote access server"
				for details). </para>
			<note>
				<para>When configuring an SSH account using a key file, note that for using key files, both
					server and client have to run RCE 7.1 or newer and that only RSA-Keys in the
					OpenSSH format are supported by RCE. You can generate such keys on Linux e.g.
					using the "ssh-keygen" tool (which creates the correct format by default). On
					Windows, you can use the software "puttygen" to generate a key (choose the type
					"SSH-2 RSA") and convert it to the OpenSSH format ("Conversions"->"Export
					OpenSSH key" in puttygen). </para>
			</note>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Configuring an RCE instance as an SSH client</title>
			<para>On the client side, SSH connections can be added in the "network" view by clicking
				"Add SSH Remote Access Connection". In the following dialog, enter the hostname and
				port of an RCE instance that provides an SSH server as well as the user name and the
				authentication data of an SSH account configured on this instance. Depending on the
				SSH account, you have to authenticate using a passphrase or by an RSA private key
				file. If your private key is protected by a passphrase, select the authentication
				type "Keyfile with passphrase protection", else select "Keyfile without passphrase
				protection".</para>
			<para>The connections are shown in the "SSH Remote Access"->"SSH Remote Access
				Connections" subtree. They can also be edited, connected and disconnected in the
				"network" view. It is possible to store passphrases using the Eclipse Secure Storage
				Mechanism. However, the changes made here are not saved in the configuration yet,
				i.e. they will be lost when RCE is closed or restarted. To permanently add SSH
				connections, you can edit the configuration file (see the "Configuration" section
				for details). However, it is not possible yet to store the passphrases for such
				connections permanently.</para>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
