<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>Component Description Page</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>On this page, the user can define characteristics for the integrated workflow
            component, for example a name and version or some information about the tool
            integrator.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>Define some characteristics for the integrated workflow. Required fields are<emphasis role="italic"> Name</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Version</emphasis>. All
            other fields are optional.</para>
        <para>Workflow component characteristics:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Name*: <emphasis role="bold">Required field</emphasis> that defines the
                        name of the component after integration. The integrated workflow component
                        is displayed with this name in the palette view. Note that the name must not
                        contain special characters. Furthermore the name will not be accepted if
                        there is another locally integrated tool or workflow component with the same
                        name.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Version*: <emphasis role="bold">Required field</emphasis> to define a
                        version for your integrated workflow component. If components with the same
                        name were integrated by other users in the network, they can be
                        distinguished by the version. When executing a workflow the user can select
                        the desired component version from a dropdown menu.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Icon Path: Select an icon for the workflow component. At best, it is larger than 32x32 pixels and has the same width and height.
                        To avoid an absolute path link to the icon, select to copy it into the configuration folder.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Group Path: Define a path here under which the workflow component is displayed in the palette view. Subgroups can be seperated by "/".</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Documentation Path: Add a documentation file for the workflow component.
                        Note that the file must be a PDF or a TXT document and it must not be
                        greater than 50 MB. The documentation will be copied into the configuration
                        folder during integration. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Description: Provide a description of the workflow component, that can be seen by other users in the network when using the component in a workflow.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Limit parallel execution: Here you can limit the number of parallel
                        executions of the workflow component. If this number is reached any further
                        calls of the component will wait until a prior call is finished. This can be
                        useful when you have restricted licenses for running the component or
                        ressource restriction is desired.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>Contact Information:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Name: Specify a contact name of the tool integrator.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>E-mail: Provide contact information if someone has questions or wants to make
                    suggestions about the integrated workflow component.</para>
            </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>
        
    </sect1>
</chapter>
