<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="first_workflow">
	<title>Running and Creating Workflows</title>
	<para>RCE is designed to execute automated workflows.
		The following steps will help you to execute provided example workflows and to create and execute your own workflow with RCE:
	</para>

	<para>Execute provided example workflows:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Start RCE.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Create a project with example workflows shipped with RCE:
				File->New->Other... Expand item
				<emphasis role="italic">RCE</emphasis>, select
				<emphasis role="italic">Workflow Examples Project</emphasis>
				and click
				<emphasis role="italic">Next</emphasis>. Give the project a name of your choice (you can leave the
				provided
				default as well) and click
				<emphasis role="italic">Finish</emphasis>. In the Project Explorer on the left-hand side your project
				appears.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Execute one of the example workflows. Double-click on a workflow of
				your choice (workflow files ends with .wf). The workflow is opened
				in the workflow editor. Right-click in workflow editor and click
				<emphasis role="italic">Execute workflow</emphasis> on the bottom of the menu
				. Confirm run configuration in the dialog by clicking
				<emphasis role="italic">Ok</emphasis>
				: The graphical representation of the executing workflow will be opened.
				Little icons indicate different states of single executing
				components.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				See the Workflow List for the current state of the workflow.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				See the Workflow Console for native console line output if
				there is some generated by a workflow.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				See the Log for log messages, e.g. info, erros, etc.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>Create your own workflow:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Open <emphasis role="italic">File->New Workflow...</emphasis> and follow the wizard dialog. In the end you will have a new workflow file, which is immediately opened in the workflow editor.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Drag <emphasis role="italic">Parametric Study</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Script</emphasis> from the workflow component palette on the right-hand side into the editor area.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Configure Script component: Double-click on Script component in the editor: Properties view is opened in the bottom.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Create a floating point (Data type: Float) input and output: Switch to <emphasis role="italic">In/Outputs</emphasis> tab. Add an input with name "incoming" of type Float. Add an output with name "outgoing" of type Float.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para> Write the underlying Python script: Switch to <emphasis role="italic">Script</emphasis>
				tab. Clear the text area. Write <code/></para>
			<para><code>value = RCE.read_input('incoming')</code></para>
			<para><code>print value</code></para>
			<para><code>RCE.write_output('outgoing', 2*value) </code>
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Configure Parametric Study: Double-click on Parametric Study component in the editor: Properties view is opened in the bottom.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Switch to <emphasis role="italic">Study Range</emphasis> tab. Double-click on the entry in the table and fill in the field to perform a parametric study from 1 to 10 in 0.5 steps.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Switch to <emphasis role="italic">Parameters</emphasis> tab. Add a parameter with name "param" of type Float.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Connect the components: Select in the palette on the right-hand side: <emphasis role="italic">Draw Connection</emphasis>. The appearance of the cursor should change. 
				Pull a connection from Parametric Study to Script by first clicking on Parametric Study and then on Script in the graphical editor.
				The connection editor opens. If the choice is unique the connection is shown automatically. 
				Otherwise: In the connection editor add a connection from <emphasis role="italic">Design Variable</emphasis> of Parametric Study to <emphasis role="italic">incoming</emphasis> of the Script. 
				In the connection editor drag a connection from <emphasis role="italic">outgoing</emphasis> of Script onto <emphasis role="italic">param</emphasis> of the Parametric Study.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Well done: You just created a workflow with a parametric study from 1 to 10 in 0.5 steps. Thereby, the generated values will be doubled by the Script component and returned to the Parametric Study component as parameters to track.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Exceute the workflow as the ones above and see Workflow Console, Workflow List, etc. for information. 
				Double-click on Parametric Study component in the runtime workflow view and you can monitor the <emphasis role="italic">param</emphasis> parameter.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

</sect1>
