<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>Excel Component Usage</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para>The Excel Component is designed to access Microsoft Excel files within RCE and to execute
            macros.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Rationale</title>
        <para>This component wraps an existing Microsoft Excel file which is linked to RCE. The
            general principle is:</para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Copy of the existing Excel file as temporarily file in a temporarily
                        folder (working copy)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Wait for all input channels which are needed to run the component
                        (depending on how input handling and constraints are set)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Execute VBA-macro “Before Excel run”</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Copy all input channels to their specific cell ranges. If there are
                        multiple values in an input channel the first value occurring will be copied
                        (“first in, first out”).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Update all formulas</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Execute VBA-macro “After input variables are written”</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Update all formulas</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Read all output channel values from their specific cell range</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Execute VBA-macro “After Excel run”</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Delete temporary Excel file</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>The Excel component has three tabs for configuration.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>File</title>
            <para>In the 'File' tab you can link an Excel file to the RCE component. Note that the
                Excel file must be located within the workflows project. Click "Link an Excel file
                ..." and navigate to the Excel file of your choice.</para>
            <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image001.png"/></para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Inputs/Outputs</title>
            <para>The 'Inputs/Outputs' tab can be used to create inputs and outputs for the Excel
                component. The configuration of the channels of both types is (mostly) similar. An
                RCE-channel is always connected to a specific Excel cell range. The button
                “Autodiscover” discovers automatically all input and output channels which are
                described as user-specific cell areas which start with “I_” for input-channels and
                with “O_” for output channels respectively.</para>
            <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image002.png"/></para>
            <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image003.png"/>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image004.png"/></para>
            <para>The following list gives a short description of all channel configuration
                    parameters:<informaltable frame="none">
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Element</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Name</entry>
                                <entry>The name of the RCE-channel</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Data Type</entry>
                                <entry>See RCE user guide (Coupling Workflow Components)</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Constraints</entry>
                                <entry>See RCE user guide (Coupling Workflow Components)</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Handling</entry>
                                <entry>See RCE user guide (Coupling Workflow Components)</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Expand Cell Area (only input channels)</entry>
                                <entry>If the user does not know the size of the cell area which she
                                    wants to insert, this field can be set to true. Now the upper
                                    left cell area field can be selected in “Address”-parameter.
                                    From that address on the complete table will be inserted,
                                    ignoring existing cell entries</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Delete empty entries (only output channels)</entry>
                                <entry>If a selected cell area contains empty rows at the end these
                                    will be cut off when setting this field to true.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Button "Select address in Excel file... "</entry>
                                <entry>To select a cell area in Excel this button opens the file in
                                    Microsoft Excel so the user can select a specific cell
                                    area.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable></para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Macros</title>
            <para>In the 'Macros' tab you can configure which VBA macros are to be run during
                runtime. </para>
            <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../images/image005.png"/></para>
            <para>When in Microsoft Excel properties the access to the VBA-project object model is
                granted the macros are available VBA macros are discovered automatrically. All
                available macros can be chosen in the respective dropdown menu.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Requirements</title>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Microsoft Excel must be installed. The component is being tested with
                        Microsoft Excel 2010.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>For an automatic detection of VBA-macros the VBA-project must be trusted.
                        Please start Excel as administrator. Navigate to file->options->trust
                        center->trust center settings->macro settings and check the "trust access to
                        the VBA project object model" option.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
