<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>Connection and Workflow Editor Usage</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>The Connection Editor is used to define the data flow between components by connecting their inputs and outputs.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Connections and Connection Editor</title>
        <para>Connections determine the data flow between workflow components. They are depicted by
            arrows. If two components are connected, there is always only a single arrow shown which can contain several
            connections. The arrowhead indicates the direction of the data flow. If data flows in both directions the arrow has two arrowheads. If data
            flows from an output of a component to an input of the same component this is called a
            self connection. Such connections are depicted by an arrow from top to bottom around the component.
            A connection can be inspected by double clicking on the arrow.</para>
        <para>There are two ways to <emphasis role="bold">draw a connection:</emphasis></para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The component palette contains a "Draw Connection" entry. Select it. Now click
                        first on the source and then on the target component in the Workflow Editor (Please note that drag and drop does not work here).
                        In the appearing dialog choose the inputs/outputs to connect. First click on
                        the output ("Source") and then on the input ("Target") to create a connection. 
                    </para>
                    <para>Alt + D is the shortcut to switch to the connection drawing tool, ALT + S
                        or ESC is the shortcut to switch to the selection tool.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the Workflow Editor's context menu or in the toolbar select "Open
                        Connection Editor" to open the Connection Editor. Here you can filter the
                        entries and draw connections.</para>
                    <para>Alt + C is the shortcut to open the Connection Editor.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Auto connect:</emphasis> When you use "Draw connection (ALT+D)"
            inputs and outputs are automatically connected when at least one of these condition is satisfied:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>There is just one input and one output <emphasis role="bold"
                            >and</emphasis> the data types are equal, independent from their
                        names.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The inputs' and outputs' names and data types are equal.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>To benefit from the auto connect feature, it is therefore useful to name inputs and outputs equally if they are planned to be
            connected.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Additional visual information:</emphasis></para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Required but not connected inputs are depicted by a red asterisk in the
                        data type icon. That means you cannot execute the workflow successfully if
                        there are red asterisks left.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Already connected inputs are depicted by a small black arrow in the data
                        type icon. That means you cannot draw another connection to an input marked
                        like that.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
