<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                         "http://docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
    <title>Runtime Workflow Editor</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <para>The Runtime Workflow Editor is used to observe and monitor the progress of the workflow execution. 
        To distinquish it from the Workflow Editor you will find the Runtime Workflow Editor with a grey background and per default without a tool palette on the righthand side.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Available Information</title>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Workflow state</emphasis>: In the title of the editor the current execution state of the workflow is shown. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Component state</emphasis>: In the top left of a component the current execution state of the component is shown. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Number of component/loop runs</emphasis>: In the top right corner of the component the number of runs is shown.
                    A single number shows the number of runs of a component. If there are two numbers divided by a slash it shows the number of loops, too.
                    For instance, 9/4 means that the outer loop of the component ran 9 times and that the inner loop ran 4 times on the last iteration.
                    Note that you will find further the runs per iteration and the overall runs if you hover the icon.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Tool run imitation mode</emphasis>: If a component runs in tool imitation mode it is shown in blue.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Disabled components</emphasis>: Note that disabled components are not shown in the Runtime Workflow Editor.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para/>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
